Hello everybody, this
is Dr. Abu Spih and I'm
here to share with you
a little more on our
osteopathic journey
through the cranium.
Osteopathy in the
cranial field.
This is Dr. Sutherland.
He attributed the knowledge or
the discovery from Dr. Still.
However, Dr. Sutherland
pursued and did a lot
of study and described a
lot of it for us and I'm
very grateful so today
we're going to talk a little
bit about diagnosing of
certain strain patterns
in the cranium you can
have strain patterns
anywhere in the body and the
cranium is not an
exception to that and we're
going to talk about some
of these treatments there
we go so um the treatments
being one of them well he
sutherland described balanced
ligamentous tension in
the body because there's a
lot of ligaments and in the
head there's membranes we
talked about the dora um the
reciprocal tension membrane
they call it sometimes
because of the reciprocal
tension between the folks
right which is kind of vertically
placed and the tentorium
which is tented but it's
somewhat horizontally placed
and just a quick reminder
so the folks attaches at
crista galley at ethmoid and
along the sagittal suture
on either side all the
way to the confluence of
sinuses which is where the
inion is and then and then
there's also a phalx cerebelli
which goes from the inion
towards foramen magnum and
it's between the two halves
of the cerebellum but then
there's also the tentorium
from the confluence of
sinuses along transverse sinus
in the back of the head
and so the occiput and
catching that posterior inferior
parietal and then parietal
across the temporal along
the petrous ridge of the
temporal on either side and
then attaching anteriorly
via the free border of the
tentorium and the attached
border of the tentorium
at the clinoid processes
of the sphenoid so they
guide and limit the motion
of the cranium so it makes
sense that that we can
motion test the strain
pattern through the dura,
gently, of course, we
don't want to induce
strain patterns.
And then we can also
treat via direct or
indirect treatments.
So direct would be
taking it to the barrier,
indirect would be taking
it to the freedom,
and then trying to
release some of the strain
so that the cranium can
have a better excursion,
inhalation and exhalation
all right and then
i mean when i say
inhalation exhalation i mean
primary respiration which
is not the breathing
respiration that's the
secondary respiration
if you have questions
about that ask me okay so
and we're also doing some
sutural release you can
release any sutures via
a v spread and directing
of the tide from the
opposite end of the skull
um but uh specifically we're
going to be talking about
occipital mastoid suture
and uh we'll talk a little
bit we well there's the
videos but we'll talk a
little bit about where to
place your hands and how to
do it to release the OM
suture because we talked
about how important that is
because of the proximity to
the jugular foramen and
through there goes cranial
nerves 9 10 and 11 and the
jugular vein and so that's
a huge import i can't
emphasize it enough i use it
in at least 95 percent of
my patients um so every
day that i'm treating and
then lastly um this is a
treatment that i'm still
understanding the far-reaching
effects of the compression
of the fourth ventricle
it's a powerhouse of a
treatment and one gets
better and better at it
every day with practice
but I think there's just
so much to discover with
why it's so useful and we'll
take a look at a little
bit about the circumventricular
organs and and
how that in some ways you
know because they're secretory
organs as well as sensory
organs and they're
kind of sensing uh through
the blood there's like a
weakened blood brain
barrier around where those
circumventricular organs
are so it's a way of
communication between the
peripheral body and the central
nervous system so it's
pretty fascinating that dr
sutherland could sense this
and realized the immense
utility of compression
of the fourth ventricle.
So,
a lot to be discovered and
a lot to be researched,
but someday all this
science will catch up to the
possibilities of osteopathy.
All right, so let's go on.
Review your landmarks. We've
done this and you've seen
it, but i left you some uh
just kind of like references
here just to glance at
again to make sure you know
where all this stuff is
because we're using it this is
just a nice reminder that
there's 22 bones in the skull
and if you count the
ossicles and the hyoid then
that's 29 it's about the
same number of bones in your
foot um and we know all the
motion with our foot and the
head has at least three
times as many articulations
143 craniofacial articulations
for motion and other
things so we want to make sure
we can treat the areas that
are restricted so our patients
can have full function
reminder here you can always
read you know any patient
history and physical is the
most important thing and
within the this cranial
concept this is no different
and once we're diagnosing
we eventually can figure out
our way to a treatment but
it's not necessarily we
think of it in terms of oh
I'm going to do this technique
where I'm going to do it and
then it's going to change
so no you want to perform
what you need to perform
to help your patient and
you're always assessing during
your treatment so you're
door assessing during your
treatment and you can reassess
all those tart changes
again afterwards yes there's
tart changes in the head
heaviness restriction
asymmetry even tissue texture
everything okay so reminders
of where to put your hands
in the vault contact because
a lot of the I mean you
can motion test the strain
patterns from any of the
contacts but when we discuss
you know air hands we usually
talk about vault so just
a quick review thumbs not
really touching the head we
know our index fingers at
the greater wing which is
close to the edge of the
eyebrow and pinky fingers if
they can on the occiput and
so then we're looking at
the strain patterns on this
page is the physiologic ones
the next page is the non
-physiologic and you really
just need to know all of
these things inside and out
so the number and direction
of axes for each strain
pattern and describing which
way the sphenoid and occiput
is moving in each kind of
strain pattern and is it a
physiologic or non and and
then the description of air
hands from a vault contact
basically if your hands are
in a contact on the head
which way is the cranium
wanting to stray like one way
or the other way and you
can kind of get the gestalt
of that just the sensing it
but then you can also get
a sense of permitted motion
by doing the motion testing
gentle motion testing we'll
go over how to do that
um yeah and then also
knowing how you name a strain
pattern you know some of them
are named for the side of
the high greater wing like
the torsion and some of them
side bending rotations
are named for the side of
convexity the fullness and um
for these the non-physiologics
they are named for the
side I mean the direction
of the basies phenoid okay
and the lateral strain one
can get a little tricky so
make sure you look at that
all right so air hands make
sure you know these and
can explain them but it's
gonna be a little different
on the head but this is just
trying to be very exaggerated
here all right so that's
the exaggeration and when
we actually do the motion
testing it's almost as if
we just think does it like
to do a right torsion you
know because sometimes just
even thinking of what a
right torsion feels like
you know that torquing where
you're say a right torsion
where your right hand is
rotating kind of posteriorly
and your left hand is rotating
kind of anteriorly so even
just thinking about that
is going to elicit all these
muscle firings and your
forearms and your hands
and you can kind of get a
sense does the patient like
to go in that direction or
not if it likes to maybe
that's the freedom and we
always name somatic dysfunctions
for the freedom so it
that could be something that
you document the somatic
dysfunction is XYZ in the
freedom but if you feel a
barrier or resistance then
that's probably not the somatic
dysfunction and we'll talk
about that more in life
all right and so once you
figure out your diagnosis
you can then go and treat
with the principle of
balanced tension so if you're
doing direct you could do
direct balanced tension or
indirect balanced tension
direct you're taking the
strain pattern towards its
barrier and holding it at
a point of balanced tension
and waiting for the body
to try to release that
tension and you just keep
chasing that point of
balance tension without letting
the strain pattern retrace
its steps back to you know
what it was because we
want to get rid of that
strain pattern so that the
cranium can be more free
and have a better excursion
so at some point you can't
really find that that
point of balance tension
anymore and you reassess and
you can wait a few cycles
of inhalation exhalation
and and that's a good way
you know you don't want to
just take your hands off
right away you can just wait
for it to kind of balance
out indirect balance tension
though is the opposite you're
taking the strain pattern
to its freedom you can liken
it to like if you have a
drawer that's stuck and
sometimes if you're trying
to pull the drawer and
it's not coming out you
know like that's you trying
to do direct balanced
tension you're trying
to just pull the drawer
out sometimes that doesn't
work and you have to
do indirect so you
actually push the drawer in
a little bit and it like
wiggles a little bit
and then it's easier to
pull back out so indirect
balanced tension is same
you're taking it to its freedom
and winding it up to a
point of balanced tension
in the freedom and and then
waiting for one release or
a few releases successive
releases sometimes it treats
so well that you really
can't find that point of
balance tension anymore and
once again you can wait a
few cycles of a better excursion
inhalation and exhalation
of the primary respiration
and you can reassess
okay I'm going to let
you watch the video
for this Dr. Ellinger
does a great job of
explaining how to do
the v-spread technique
it's just important
to note that you want
to have your index
finger and your middle
finger on either
side of the occipital
mastoid sutra that
seems most restricted
and you can check to
see which one's most
restricted by putting
your fingers in a V and
just trying to spread it
out to see which side's
heavier, more compressed,
more restricted.
You treat the more
restricted side
first. Your other
hand that's on the
direct opposite
side on the frontal,
that's going to, same thing,
not a major fluid wave,
but it's almost like you
just think about sending a
fluid wave towards your hand
that has the v shape towards
that suture and then what
happens is that fluid
wave will start to go back
and forth between your hands
until you get a sense of
softening and opening of that
that suture and then you
want to recheck and very
often that side is more
free the other side is more
jealous and you'll very
often need to check and treat
the other side okay same
thing just more one more
description of it and this
is just a picture of the
circumventricular organs within
the central nervous system
it's worth it to maybe just
go watch a video or or do
a little more research to
see how amazing these little
structures are because
they're they're in areas where
the blood brain barrier
is is weaker so it allows
for a sampling between the
cerebral spinal fluid and
the the arterial system so
you know take for example
area postrema if there's
any toxins in the blood that
is one of the first areas
that will pick that up and
it's uh can trigger a vomiting
reflex so it's defensive
so there's sensory
circumventricular organs and
there's secretory circumventricular
organs so it's basically
keeping our body there
they keep our body in
homeostasis so um what better
way to access like the major
functions of the body whether
it's you know cardiovascular
and blood pressure related
or osmolarity related
or electrolyte and fluid
balance right or at the
pineal body which is helping
us take care of our sleep
-wake cycle and circadian
rhythms or if it's at our
posterior pituitary which
helps to secrete the oxytocin
and antidiuretic hormone
so so many functions are
impacted by these circumventricular
organs so we'll talk
about how we do the compression
of the fourth ventricle
and the whole point is
you know dr southern talks
about like compressing the
fourth ventricle by like
squeezing the bulb like so
this area where the cerebellum
and the brain stem are
sandwiching basically the
fourth ventricle well when
you're applying a little
compression at the occiput
which is that's where the area
we're talking about you
know you're at the occiput
inferior to the inian and
medial to either both of
the occipital mastoid sutures
as you do that we know
that the volume within this
cavity is staying constant
so if you're adding a
little more pressure then
um you know like the the
volume that's within this
cavity has to go somewhere
so there's pressure put on
to the um the ventricular
system and so that's putting
the csf and in more
uh contact with these
circumventricular organs and
so they're more able to perform
their homeostatic functions
so some of the reasons
why people will do a cv4
well one is like the old
timer said you don't know
what to do do a cv4 or you
know it's a great place to
start a treatment and it's
a great place to end the
treatment so you know you
can see by the slide used
to relieve headaches used
to relieve fever or help
with fever and assist with
difficult and stalled labor
so obstetric that's used
a lot it's a lot of times
associated with obstetrics
they've done studies
where people installed and
ineffective contractions
stalled labor when you do a
cv4 it helps the process
happen relieving congested
sinuses lungs it helps to
reduce edema if you have
somebody with a lot of like
extra swelling in the body
definitely try a cv4 it's
good to help reduce the
effects of trauma somebody
with a whiplash because it
like there's a big strain
in the fascias everywhere
it's a good idea to try
to do a cv4 if you do a
somatic you know if you just
do like a structural exam
and you get a sense of all
their somatic dysfunctions
if you do a cv4 and you
go recheck them a lot
of times you'll find the
secondary somatic dysfunctions
will have disappeared
so just helps to augment
health and healing and
relaxes the patient in many
ways yeah so I like this
picture because you can
really see where the hand
placement should be so inferior
to the indian and medial
to the occipital mastoid
processes and you can
watch the video and if you
want a more in-depth video
dr ellinger did a little
more in-depth video and
very useful to watch both
of those so sutherland
described what was happening
at a cv4 so you can see
the top hand that's the you
know you can cradle one hand
on top of the other or some
people just depending on
your hand size some people
just like to use one hand and
you know with their fingers
on one side and their
hypothenar on the other side
but the idea is to get that
part of the occiput which
i'll show you on this page
i'll show you with the pen
let's see if we can get
the pen nice all right
so let's just outline
the occiput right so this
is our these are our
occipital mastoid sutras
so this is mastoid
obviously mastoid and
mastoid so this would be
our temporal bone that
way and this is part of
our other temporal bone
all that's temporal
um okay and so then
here we go sorry
here's our occiput
all the way this way sorry
occiput here's our inion and
so we want to stay inside
of these occipital mastoid
switches we don't want to
be on them we want to have
our thenar eminence is about
here and hereish and when
we compress the occiput all
right we're bringing our
thenar eminence is kind of
that way and that way okay
we're compressing the occiput
medially and so in some of
this the descriptions it
talks about uh causing an
extension well what happens
in extension of the occiput
every well everything in the
head narrows in extension
right and so the occiput
is also the squama of the
occiput is also narrowing so
but what you're really doing
is compressing the occiput
right and so you're
compressing it because of the
structures okay so if this is
the occiput out here these
are the structures that we're
trying to affect you know
with the csf going up and
down etc so if you're
compressing this area here you're
trying to get that csf in
better contact with those
circumventricular organs
in order to better do their
job right because as a
physician we don't know how to
do the body's job better
than the body does but we
can find where there is
somatic dysfunction and try to
assist relieving the somatic
dysfunction but this is
kind of like sometimes it
can be a stimulatory and
sometimes it can be palliative
in the body so um yeah
so just in conclusion
we'll just remind ourselves
of all the possible
indications for osteopathy in
the cranial field anything
from headaches we said
whiplash injuries traumatic
brain injury concussive
symptoms any dizziness
vertigo tinnitus even high
-pitched tinnitus tends
to be they describe it as
internally rotated
temporal versus low-pitched
tinnitus supposedly externally
rotated temporal thinking
about things like that
and any cranial neuropathy
along anywhere having
to do with the brainstem
or the dura right so you
have cranial nerve six
can get entrapped or four
and get like strabismus,
you can get anosmia
actually with the
cranial nerve 1 around
the ethmoid. You can
get trigeminal neuralgia
obviously and you
can get Bell's palsy
and cranial nerve 7.
With any otitis media
or ear infections you
want to make sure you
look at the cranium,
the temporal bone, and other
places, sinusitis, TMJ,
colicky babies,
you want to look
also at that trigular foramen,
plagiocephaly, torticollis,
you want to make
sure you look at the
condyles, and same thing
with the feeding difficulties,
cranial nerve 12,
any pathology involved with the
vagus, so also any
cardiac symptoms,
any, you know, heart rate,
blood pressure respiratory
issues anybody with asthma
etc or gastrointestinal
system symptoms GERD or nausea
and then the jugular vein
and we talked about brain
fog or neurodegenerative
diseases you know how is
this all tying in together
eye complaints infections
even glaucoma you know there's
seven bones in the orbit
so how does an injury or
trauma to the eye impact its
proper function and drainage
what about that cell
aturcica in the sphenoid and
the pituitary in the
neuroendocrine immune system so
looking at all this stuff
there's a lot of reasons why
i would use this and even
obstetrics in gynecology.
So looking forward to
doing some of these things
with you and practicing in
lab and hopefully at home.
And these are some
of our references and
Dr. Sutherland. And
so make sure you watch
all the videos and
make sure to leave us
feedback and let us
know how we can help you
learn this material
better. Have a great day.
quick addendum this is
unilateral temporal contact
another hold that you'll be
introduced to in lab and just
like all the other contacts
you need to be relaxed in
your body so comfortable
so that you take the strain
out of your body so that you
are most able to sense what
is going on in these
subtle motions within your
patient's cranium this one is
designed specifically to get
a sense of what is happening
at either temporal bone.
And first talking about
the setup, you can
sit at the corner of
the table, that way your
quadrad hand, the one
that's behind the occiput,
you can rest the inion,
also known as external
occipital protuberance, in
the palm of your hand and
your middle finger and the
rest of your palm of your
hand will be along that
superior nuchal line and
the head will rest comfortably
there and then your
other hand that is contacting
the temporal the middle
finger can rest on that
that external acoustic
meatus of the ear and then
with your index finger
and your thumb you can
get like a little pincer
grasp of the zygomatic
portion of the temporal bone.
And then four and five
can rest on the mastoid
tip and the mastoid
portion with the
pinky. So the tip is with
the fourth finger and
the mastoid portion
with the fifth finger.
And so then once you've
got an idea of where all
those fingers go, then
you need to relax your
hand so you can try to
sense the temporal motion.
So once you are at the
temporal, please disregard
what I'm about to tell
you and just sense
what is actually happening
at the temporal bone.
But since many of
you would like to
have an idea, the
temporal bone is
known as the
troublemaker of the head.
It's a gets restricted it
can have untoward effects
in the body and if you
think about all of the
cranial nerves that are
associated with the temporal
you have four and six
that have to do with your
ocular muscles that are
involved with the area where
the temporal and the sphenoid
are coming together as
well as the tentorium and
the leaves of the tentorium
so they can get irritated
or compressed there
especially if the
temporal is severely
internally or
externally rotated.
Also cranial nerve 5 as
you know is a trigeminal
and that's like within
Meckel's cave and that
rests on the petrous
portion of the temporal.
Cranial nerves 7 and 8 we
know have to do with hearing
as well as the ******
nerve is number 7. So those
go through the temporal
bone. And then 9, 10, and 11
come out from the jugular
foramen which is between
the temporal and the
occiput. So any number of
restrictions or displacement
of the temporal bone can cause
a lot of problems from
difficulty draining, so otitis
media problems, or tinnitus
ringing in your ear,
hearing and balance problems.
Yeah, so we talked
about Pinto's ligament
and that petrosphenoid
ligament. So there's
a lot of tentorial
interplay there. There's
a lot of issues that
can happen there.
And then there's the
attachments of the temporal.
And so the temporal motion
is driven by the occiput.
That's something noteworthy.
And there's connections
at the sphenosquamous
pivot, so with the sphenoid.
There's connections with
the mandible at the TMJ.
There's connections
with the zygoma,
so that corner
clamp of the face.
And then, of course, parietal
rests superiorly
to the temporal.
So there's a lot of
connections, you know,
kind of that have to
happen together. So as the
midline bones, namely
sphenoid, occiput,
ethmoid, are going into
flexion and extension,
the temporal is
one of the paired
lateral parts. So it
undergoes an external
rotation and an
internal rotation.
And the axis of motion
goes along the petrous
part of the bone and
then out through there.
So that motion, as the
occiput is coming forward
into flexion, It's
driving that petrous
part of the temporal into
an external rotation.
So you get the
temporals on either side
tipping in a wobbly
wheel kind of fashion.
The superior part of it will go
anterolateral as the
petrous portion kind of
comes up during that
inhalation phase.
and then the
reverse will happen
during the exhalation phase,
otherwise known as extension
of the midline parts and
internal rotation of the
bilaterally paired parts.
And I think that
will do it for this
addendum. We will
go over this more
in class and show
you how to do it.